[Music]
so at the risk of overthinking an
internet meme we're going to talk about
the NPC meme which is definitely broken
through into the mainstream over the
last couple of days probably when a BBC
article about it New York Times article
about it social media starting to
respond often twitter band a few
accounts and link it to something that
one of our contributors Jordan green
hall has said before we'd put out a few
things recently with Jordan greenhorn
he's definitely one of our favorite
thinkers and he talks about this idea of
thinking versus simulated thinking I
think this really helps to kind of
identify what's going on and why there's
some truth in it and why actually the
truth is kind of the truth effect at the
moment it's kind of used to attack the
left but I think it points to something
quite fundamental about the way we
interact with the world so to start off
by saying what the MPC mean is I'm not a
gamer you're a gamer well is it yeah so
an NPC in a game is a non-player
character so as you're playing a game
you're obviously encountering characters
in that game who are computer-generated
and they can be quite sophisticated so
you can interact with them and they
might have a set of responses I mean
they do have a set of responses they are
obviously they're running a script and
you might encounter one go off and do
something else
encounter that same NPC later and they
they just repeat the same thing they
said before because they don't have free
will or agency and so I guess the joke
of the meme and I and what the why the
meme has been so reacted against so
strongly is that it the suggestion is
that people particularly who are heavily
engaged with identity politics they
don't have free will
they're they're running a script and
they have stock responses to to
everything and I think that that whole
idea of you have no free will I think
that's the thing that's really gotten
under people's skin
why because I mean it's absolutely core
to being to your identity our identity
our I think our egos identity is based
in large part
and that we are free agents in the world
and we're making our own decisions so I
think there's nothing more there's
something that gets under anyone's skin
more than than suggesting that you are
you're effectively like part of the
matrix you are running a script you're
not you're not a unique individual well
it's interesting you mentioned the
matrix because Jordan green Hall
appeared in the film glitch in the
matrix that we we put out earlier this
year and that was about the the Jordan
Peterson Kathy Newman interview which i
think is the is still the sort of
perfect example of of this sort of idea
of simulated thinking because whatever
he said there was a kind of it was like
she was running a computer program and I
think Jordan Greenhill said that after
in the grillage in the Matrix film there
was a kind of input/output and it didn't
fit he didn't fit into the box that she
was kept trying to ascribe into and but
she never actually engaged what he was
saying so that's a really good kind of
example of it but generally we're gonna
play a quick clip now from Jordan
talking about thinking versus simulated
thinking simulated thinking I'm proposin
happens when something breaks down this
ability to fluidly participate in both
modes and in fact maybe even more
precisely is went habit mode there shows
up as and presents itself as thinking
and this is where it gets very dangerous
where one is simulated thinking the
individual actually may believe possibly
quite earnestly that they are in fact
actually thinking when what they're
doing is actually running some kind of
script some kind of habit and of course
oftentimes some kind of script there was
not necessarily even theirs in the first
place they're running a third party
script malware as it were so the key
point in this isn't just that there are
two forms of thinking one is habit mode
and one is explorer mode it's that
sometimes habit mode is the right way to
to interact with the world often it is
and Explorer mode is labore
it takes time it's not useful the
problem with simulated thinking is when
the wrong method is used when habit mode
is used when Explorer mode is required
and that's usually when the situation
has changed especially when the culture
has changed which we would argue it has
and the the methods that have been used
up until now in the culture especially
is kind of defense strategy from a lot
of people on the left of accusing other
people of being bigoted sexist racist
when they get on to topics they don't
like is no longer functioning and I
think that's the really interesting part
is that simulated thinking works well
when when the environment is not
changing the environment is clearly
changing very significantly especially
if you're on on the left and you've been
hit by bricks that you've been hit by
Trump really we've said this quite a few
times it's like if you if you haven't
started kind of questioning some of how
the way that you're acting in the world
has that has contributed to these things
that you were not expecting and not
wanting to happen then what will it take
for you to kind of think of we've talked
about the shadow of liberalism which is
this sort of tribalism that doesn't want
to admit that it's tribalism and also
kind of amygdala hijacking which is an
interesting idea as well which is you
know the amygdala is as part of the
brain very old part of the brain which
is really involved in our
fight-or-flight response and just can
take us over because it's based on our
survival so anything that threatens our
identity or like our tribal identity as
well the amygdala can come in and we're
ready to fight or run away I'm actually
like our pupils get bigger at our blood
goes to our limbs and we're just
completely charged up impossible to have
real thinking in that mode you can't
when your sympathetic nervous systems
going crazy
you can't think straight like oh and we
are all prone to it I get into that mode
sometimes when I get really angry on
Facebook it tends to be online actually
which is the interesting thing yeah and
so that and then this this idea I think
Brett Weinstein talked about around it's
pretty like it's pretty terrifying for
us on a deep level biologically to say
something that goes against the tribe
and I want like this kind of similarity
of thinking is in large part I think a
way to make sure that you stick with the
tribe because going into the tribe in
the past
would have been an existential threat
but falling out with your tribe and
that's sort of deep-rooted in to us is
that it if you fell out with your tribe
in any way that was probably the end of
you yeah so I think Brett said this
again is that we have to be able to
evolve past the tools we've been given
by evolution if we're going to survive
because the old programs that we're
running are not fit for the modern world
and are probably well not even probably
I think it's a definitely
self-destructive so I find it's really
interesting like if we're in a debate
mode kind of the implicit frame as I'm
trying to to beat you we're gonna play
another clip from Jordan Greenhalgh
debate we normally do is very much in
there in the direction of a habit mode
and as a consequence can quite often
fall into simulated thinking and what a
debater is engaging in a pattern
recognition and rapid response activity
with perhaps a specific small amount of
focused thinking controlling the
structure I think we should be clear
that the primary utility is investing
someone in a social conversation and
that is at a halt conducive to
collaborative thinking so that what ends
up happening is that when someone shows
up who's actually trying to engage in
collaborative thinking and someone else
deploys the toolkit of debate the
debater will show up as winning at least
to those who aren't watching closely and
the thinker will show up as being
oftentimes really rather stupid and so
nobody wants to emulate that and so what
is up happening is that it begins to
select against thinking in both
directions which is to say people who
are trying to take lose and other people
don't even try because it just looks
like a bad choice and this shows up all
over the place you know the political
infighting is of this sort what he's
saying is that the strategies that are
selected for in that environment are
kind of running a script it's running
good strategy it's running
this then this and then in that frame
simulated thinking starts being selected
for when you say this I know that I can
respond with this and that will win the
debate we're not in a place of exploring
the question and if someone shows up
who's actually trying to explore the
question to think in public then that
person will look like a moron because
they're not they're not playing the same
game but then that environment starts to
select against genuine thinking and that
has been happening for an awfully long
time which is which ties into the whole
intellectual darkweb concept because the
intellectual darkweb if it's anything is
the idea that we can think in public and
I guess part of it comes from the trust
that they have going on each other shows
and knowing each other and then they're
able to explore ideas knowing that no
one's going to try and catch them out or
kind of throw insults at them and say
well talking about gender difference
between between men and women you're
you're sexist or whatever but I think
that's really really interesting because
I think that same process has happened
in many different industries what Eric
Weinstein calls the gated institutional
narrative which is a sort of sort of
self-protection thing where genuinely
novel thinking it starts to be selected
against and starts to be a losing
strategy for people in these in
institutions yeah I agree with that I
think there's also what's been
interesting to watch is this kind of
accusation that the NPC me meme is
dehumanizing because implicit in the
ability to have a you know a
conversation a collaborative
conversation is the idea that we meet
each other with a certain level of human
human respect even if we disagree and
there's been a lot of pushback from you
know those spreading the meme saying
well we were dehumanized we got accused
of being Russian BOTS
it's like yeah I can see that we already
Huma knows each other all the time
it's happening on both sides and it's
part of it happens as well I mean we
even do it in workshops that's what we
tell people to look for when trying to
find the shadow that one of their
shadows you know we all have many
shadows it's where do we feel like total
contempt
where we think this person is less than
human and it's happening constantly and
that is something that if we are going
to actually get into a place where we
can have these collaborative
conversations while still disagreeing
with one another it's essential that we
come from a place of recognizing shared
humanity at the very least like that's
kind of a baseline because otherwise and
we're kind of screwed it doesn't go
anywhere it can't go anywhere it's you
know it just gets further and further
into the other is not human but I am
this is another concept that Jordan
greenhalgh talks about that what we need
to create is collective intelligences
that no one of us will be able to come
up with the idea so we need to generate
a collective intelligence and the only
way of doing that is through
collaborative thinking it's through I
think this you taking what I'm saying
and then building on it and building on
it and building on it in this generative
way and if we're if we're playing the
same rival risk divisive trying to beat
each other which kind of any YouTube
comments thread or any kind of Facebook
argument then what we're doing you can
win that game but then you're just
winning you're winning a game of quoits
on the Titanic as the ship is sinking
and I think that's true on a on a kind
of interpersonal level something like
Jordan Pederson talks about well yeah
you can you can dominate your wife if
you want to if you want to kind of win
an argument what does winning an
argument mean in a relationship well it
probably means not winning being right
and then then resenting you for the next
20 years it means how do you win in a
way that keeps the health of the system
and that's what I think he was also
pointing to with his into his
[Music]
interjection about cavanaugh was how do
we have an outcome that it that works
for the health of the system rather than
working just for one site beating the
other again maybe that wasn't
appropriate people have their different
views on that but I think that was the
context that he was coming from of how
do you have an outcome from this but
that doesn't add to the already
kind of existential threats of
polarization and partisanship that we've
got in the system already yeah and I
think it that brings up something that I
think it was maybe like a common theme
of what we're talking about right here
which is it's it's about how we think
not what we think like we're very
focused on what people think and so much
of this is so much progress is gonna be
around how we think and then also where
we think ok because I noticed like I
really struggle with that kind of
dehumanizing of the other online
especially you know I really I have to
prevent myself typing comments I have to
you know I notice it happening in myself
I notice the kind of righteous anger I
don't really get it in person I mean I
couldn't meet the same person in person
and I have a completely different like
oh yeah man just disagree with them but
they're say she's cool he's cool you
know and just get get into a place
that's almost immediately much more
collaborative because it's human human
and so yeah how and where we think I
think that's you know part of the next
frontier so we're gonna put some of the
clips that we've talked about including
the jordan green hall one in the show
notes and if you enjoyed this and you
want to get early access to some other
great films please consider becoming a
patron and do you see